So our first talk today is
by the one and only Joseph Katsioloudes.
Joseph is a senior developer
advocate at a company called GitHub.
Raise your hand if you have heard of GitHub.
Okay.
Okay, so you're getting a little traction.
Good for you guys. Really proud of you.
So no pressure to speakers after this.
But Joseph has spoken in over 25 countries
and has over 2.8 million views on his videos.
Again, no pressure, but he is a seasoned pro so you're in very good hands.
Can we get a little round of applause for Joseph, please?
Take it away.
Okay.
Good morning everybody.
Well, perfect.
Welcome to Code Security Reinvented.
Navigating the area of artificial intelligence.
My goal
today is to show you practical ways to use artificial intelligence for security
use cases. Whatever I show you, you can do.
Also, in Claude Code, Codex — not just GitHub Copilot.
Okay. Let's get started.
Yeah.
180 million plus developers.
A platform that builds scales, secure software.
Specifically, my team
is that the GitHub Security Lab, which is a team of security experts
with the mission to secure the open source software that we all rely on.
And we do this through research, education and other activities.
For instance, this is some research from last year about bypassing Ruby SAML.
Just last week we showed how somebody
could exploit seven zip with a heap buffer overflow.
We have found an help fix more than 1000 vulnerabilities,
900 plus of which have been given unique CVEs.
And the most important thing is that we help people fix those.
We don't just report them.
And this is important
because exactly, there is a gap between security and developers.
If we try to quantify this gap, there is just one application
security specialist for every 100 software developers.
This gap is the opportunity that we can help minimize with AI.
However, if we are not equipped with the right knowledge,
the gap maybe is going to widen or it's not going to close
because we didn't maximize our potential there.
And that's the point of this talk.
I want to show you the pros and cons, the drawbacks of AI,
so you can make a human in the loop use case of how you can use it responsibly.
So this is the first statement AI can help minimize the security gap.
Let's see how the first thing is writing safer code.
For me this is very important because all my career so far, I'm
hearing from senior leaders in cyber security about shifting left.
The problem when you shift left is that you keep having a gap on the left.
The whole point and the opportunity here is to start
left, and starting left means a lot of things.
And of course it has to touch in the developers
how the code is being built in the first place.
I brought some demos that are starting from the beginning of this
AI wave that we are living in so slowly, slowly
we can come up to date with releases up to two days ago or up to Friday.
So let's get started.
The code might be a bit small to it, clearly at the back
I'm gonna show you with lasers and I'm going to read everything.
So we are all on the same page.
The first example I want to show you is from the first releases
of AI, with a chat on the left.
Here we have an example of vulnerable code.
On the right you can see a very simple SQL injection on line 23.
It comes from the fact that line 22 has a variable that is user
controlled, that is not being sanitized.
But the first thing I want to show you with that is I'm
asking an early version of copilot.
What is wrong with this code?
What are the security issues here?
And right straight away I want to highlight that
out of the three responses that are here, they are solutions.
So this one passwords in plain text.
Yeah absolutely. They are SQL injection.
There is no input validation but there is no password in plain text.
And with that I wanted to show you that we suffered from hallucinations
and we will never get away with zero hallucinations.
The second thing I want to show you is non-deterministic at its best.
So I'm bringing in a code base of ten security vulnerabilities.
I'm asking the same question in my context.
I have the whole code base, and with that, I get back eight results.
I get back eight results.
Somebody can tell me, yeah, you get eight results back.
You have 80% accuracy.
However, that's not the case and I will not make it more specific here.
Number six, somebody can read prototype
pollution in JavaScript, which happens when a method
such as the array function is inheriting something from the parent method.
And when the parent is poisoned, you get down to the children method.
And because I was so impressed by that one, I have put in context
the specific file that was suffering from that pollution, and I asked the exact
same question with the difference that this vulnerability never came up,
I reduced the context and it didn't come up.
So this is non-deterministic at its best.
Someone could tell me that I can run this many times
and find out more and more, but this just adds to the friction
and to the false positive I have to go through.
Then I tried to change the model and see if that improves the situation at all,
but it didn't because the pollution didn't come up.
And with that, I will not mention that it's not about models,
it's about the rest of things specifically in AI,
in in security models can definitely help, but you can achieve
more when you have better scaffolding and we are going to go there as well.
Now the next thing I was thinking in the early days
was, okay, but what if we can still achieve something?
And always I was trying to fix the problems that we are pointed out
by AI, because in cybersecurity, and I want you to remember that
we don't have a detection problem in cybersecurity.
We have a fixing problem.
We have so much ways to find what's wrong, and we don't have the ways
to minimize that gap by get up to the fixing speed.
So by that, I started to realize that
maybe I can use something else for detection,
and then I can use AI to be the reasoning layer and help me fix things.
So the next thing I started to do was, okay, let's be more agent.
Slowly, slowly focus a bit on security.
The results have definitely improved, but always there was this non determinism
and the the nation's coming into play and slowly, slowly
we are getting up to speed with the latest developments in AI.
Before that I want to mention
that AI can definitely help minimize the security gap.
But in our view as a GitHub security lab, it's not here
to replace the human in the loop or skip security testing entirely.
However, AI is definitely changing the scene
of security testing now.
You should be always following good security.
Hygiene and AI shouldn't be your only safety net.
And with that, I'm going to make a bridge to MCPs.
Model context protocol.
The Model Context protocol, designed by,
was designed in order to help the
AI models to go outside of their small
and narrow training books, help us access server side
information from companies that we are using, and so on.
I can speak for a long time about why you should be careful with MCP and so on.
I assume that by now we are in a good shape, and the protocol
is help improving itself and taking steps towards more secure direction.
I just want to mention that I'm going to assume that for the rest of them,
you have a good security hygiene of installing MCP servers
in tools that you already trust, and you are not going to go out there
in the wild and trust your contacts with overly broad scopes and stuff like that.
So let's see that MCP
can they help make security better and fight with those problems?
Yes and no.
So number one thing, when you detect issues with AI, yes.
They are not deterministic.
It made me a higher dollar cost because the cost is variable.
However you can use it as the reasoning layer.
You can use it for systematic issues. Contextual issues.
It's easier to model.
You can ask questions.
Am I using the right cryptographic primitives?
Is there any sensitive data on the client side?
These things you will never be able to do with traditional static security
tooling such as CodeQL and others.
Because these can model everything and they can detect stuff on client side.
However, before, however, they are
checking stuff on a pattern matching way.
Right.
But right now what are the trending security issues in AI?
It's all about behavior stuff.
For example, something can be amazing, syntactically correct, and pass
all these pattern checks, but at the same time it can lick
the whole stuff we have internally because the behavior is wrong.
At the same time, they have a fixed cost, they have high confidence,
and they are more mature, so we can still be able to use them with one.
We covered it.
It was all about you following what you already trust for MCP.
And with that, I want to give you the example of the GitHub MCP server.
I can go in more detail with other MCP, but I prefer to choose a company
if I say something wrong. At least it's my company.
So for security specifically, you have some functions
such as code security, secret production, security advisories.
These are gonna pull server side findings and bring them to either
your CLI, your IDs, and the whole point of this is about transcribe.
You translate these findings into outcomes so that the
AI model, the agent can reason with more context.
Using the latest findings on your GitHub account or other companies
you are going to use for.
So therefore this is going to help to extend the context.
It can help you reason about your actions
in a way that is more focused.
Let's now go to the next step about skills.
So when it comes to skills,
think about it this way with this specific diagram.
Let's start from the bottom actually.
So if I have an MCP, I can get access
to my scanners results to issues that are there
maybe to seem basically in every functionality out there.
But if you have MCP without skills that are going to give structure,
your AI agents are just going to have capability.
But without your process, if you have just skills
such as, for example, this is what you should be doing
in one, two, three, four and you don't have MCP.
Maybe here you don't have enough power to execute what you want to execute.
And of course, MCP servers can come up in the skills
being processed being analyzed there.
And the good thing with skills
is that you can have them in a way that they are auditable, audible,
maintainable, extensible in the skill registry.
So in the security world, some use cases for you is that.
Oh, I found something with my code scanning, I'm going to
be able to pull that information and issue is going to be created.
My copilot,
Codex Claude Code is going to fix that thing,
propose this fix in the PR, and then I'm going to be able
to be the human in the review coming in this case here,
in order to release and keep up my CI/CD.
If something else needs to be added there, you can use a skill
for the triage logic and of course to extend into more capabilities.
You can use the MCP player here.
I'm going to show you an example of the CI/CD.
From the moment that you can't push code, and I want to name
that fine and fix security issues in the traditional way.
Before AI, somebody could go in their dashboards
such as for example, this one from code QL.
That is a GitHub solution.
You can't see a list of what is wrong with your code
alongside the severities, and when you have that,
you are going to see some explanations that are always the same.
They are not going to be specific to your code, right?
There is no way I up to this point.
I'm showing you the past so that you can appreciate the now in the now
fixes are coming to the PR of course this is Copilot auto fix.
You can have the same functionality with other AI systems.
Of course.
Here you get an explanation that is based
on the deterministic findings that happen from the SaaS tools.
Of course, you can have a layer of
AI finding things and connecting the context
you have there with the with your goals and all the things you want to have
that are out of scope for this unit AI to do right.
And the latest plugin from Afterpay just three days ago was trying just to do that.
I'm going to cover that in a bit.
So here I get an explanation of why this is highlighted.
You get proposed code that is going to fix this ability, all the PR.
And then here on the PR level, you can continue to commit directly
to remove this vulnerability. You can edit on the PR.
And then once you do that you are good to keep going.
I want to share something.
So I'll work for GitHub.
For the past four and a half years, a big learning I had is that developers
have to be working on one place, and this should be the pull request.
Of course, with products like Codex or the new app from GitHub
Copilot, you can have everything in an application.
However, the moment
you give developers more power and they have to log in on the X website
and the Y website, there's friction and is not a long term sustainable.
So by being in the PR, we managed and our clients
as well to become three times faster when it comes to fixes.
Because remember in AI, in security we have a fixing problem.
We don't have a detection problem.
So GitHub fixed 600 vulnerabilities in two weeks, bringing the fixed
rate to the top, and then the clients have achieved the same.
The next big thing is agentic workflows.
I'm going to get the question I'm sure okay.
So if we are using agentic workflows for security, what's the point
of using SaaS tooling or other security tools?
The answer is all the things we saw before
with non-deterministic and the maturity and the other stuff.
However, the big advantage of this one is tailoring.
And I'm going to show you exactly what this means.
So here we are going to see a basic example.
We have a security agent that is being set up in this agent.
I gave exactly what is out of scope, what I care about,
what how our company is doing stuff, and then I'm running this agent.
These vulnerabilities are going to be picked up only by AI on the code level.
And then somebody can create issues about them, or somebody can choose
to fix them on the spot in the same place that the code is being developed.
And here is the script you can see.
Let's go back on this one.
Oh, I'm on the presenter mode okay.
Basically what what I wanted to show you here is that you can change the script
the way you want, and the AI agent is going to deterministically
as much as possible, follow exactly what you try to achieve with your script.
You still have to be careful with this stuff,
because if you put let's speak about style now, okay?
And taste.
So I noticed that if I put every instruction I have
and all the rules and all the things that apply to my team in one script,
I'm definitely bloating the AI context and the process is not the best.
Therefore, I realize that some things should be going into agents, some other
things should be part of these files, and some others should be just on tooling.
I can speak three hours about this thing, so let's keep it at the end
if I have time. Now
let's see how you can be on your repo
and you can create an agent workflow straight straight on there.
The good thing with these workflows
is that they can either run on a schedule or they know them selves.
When to run because they understand what's going to trigger them.
They run in the same VMs as GitHub actions.
And the whole idea is that you have a smart agent tracking
and waiting for something to happen through a workflow.
Then of course, it's not about just security.
You have the chance to have productivity gains as well.
On the left I put in general here I put two different workflows
you can take directly from the free online library of GitHub workflows.
Here we have one that is going to help you with automatic reviews
of what's coming in and on the right.
I can't really read it.
Yeah, so is a trial issue cookie master.
So trying to try out everything that comes in now.
You heard about Claude Mythos from Anthropic and all the capabilities it has found.
Raise your hands. Perfect.
So my team has access to that and of course
access to other models.
And we try to find vulnerabilities with that.
And we try to open source our knowledge of how to do that.
So with these models, these models don't find the vulnerabilities by themselves.
Right.
It's also security people steering them
and codifying their knowledge in what is called task flows.
And we did exactly that in order to help you find
what we did was that we have quantified knowledge.
We have from our security researchers that found all these vulnerabilities
in a way that you can open this
repo you have in a code space.
And when you do so, we are going to run
our manual security reviews in a way that is automated by AI.
And then you can have
being shown to you.
You can access that at gh.io/taskflows.
It's free is open source,
and it's how vulnerabilities are being found at the end of the day.
From powerful models with security researchers steering them.
Next one I want to highlight, because it's all about supply chain
these days, is how somebody yourself or your agents
can take better informed supply chain decisions.
We tried a lot of things, but my risk appetite aligns with this approach.
I will not show you now.
It might be less need that I wanted, but it it matches the quality
of something I will be confident to ship in front of you. So
how to
make supply chain decisions like be honest here.
How many of you are spending more than three minutes in deciding
if they should introduce something in their code or not?
You spend more than three.
Is it more than 30 minutes?
But perfect.
Okay, so to speed up your research about this,
we have put together for instruction files that you can extend.
They are free and open source.
The URL is in the next slide.
The whole point is for you to get this executive summary
with visa emojis showing you what you have to be careful of.
We are using sources of information that we are happy about,
and in here you can go to the killings and find out for yourself.
This is at gh.io/risk
in order for you to make good security decisions.
As we are running slowly, slowly, out of time,
I want to remind you that with AI you can have security guidance
and this is something you should never underestimate.
I did the same thing in the CLI.
The results.
We are very similar,
but I want to show you this on the web because it's easier to visualize.
I went in a project called bootstrap, the open source project
that is a project I'm considering to use on my supply chain.
And I asked the question what I should be careful
about in this project, if I use it or if I use it.
Basically, and this is the number one question people are asking us when we run
office hours with open source projects.
How can somebody hack me?
The results here, I run it with different models are consistent.
It's a security person
telling you what you should be careful when you start
using this project, so that you don't have to review all that code yourselves.
You can go to the specific URLs and start saving time.
Let's go fast over this.
So fasting is a technique that you can use to cause
undesirable behavior in your code.
You can use any tooling for this.
And the whole point is that security.
Security engagements get really slow with fuzzing, right?
Because security person like myself have to produce millions of inputs
in order to cause undesirable behavior in AI is amazing.
With that, AI can create these millions of inputs and the boilerplate
and also the harness, which also slows down these engagements
and hack your code in a safe way and tell you what you can improve.
So you don't just do these things in a static way.
AI reading code and is non-deterministic.
I mean, even if your code is being attacked, you can still benefit.
Even if there is no determinism and hallucinations,
you can still find a lot of findings there.
Always remember that privacy is important.
That's why GitHub Copilot Center is there with Q&A on how you can.
I mean, these days you are interested about certificates
and is my context going to leak and stuff like that.
All is being answered there.
And with that, I prepare a playground for you to try everything here for free.
You can just get started in two minutes right from your browser.
By navigating to that,
I created a bot like it's a CLI.
It looks and feels like OpenClaw and the rest of agents like that.
It's inside code spaces.
They are for sandbox already.
You can ask it to do some things like create this
file, access this simulated internet we put together.
I also put in agentic workflows there as well that you can access
stocks information in Bloomberg and like the simulated Bloomberg
and find stuff out and also Mati agent abilities.
So you can play and understand
what can go wrong before you use the real tooling out there.
There are some pre-training as well you can have where I put together
a chat bot that in natural language,
you might ask for it to leak some secrets.
It shouldn't leak.
You don't have to know how to code.
You don't have to be a security expert.
You can just use natural language and see for yourself what's happening there.
And trust me, it's not 2025 stuff.
It's the latest stuff.
If you say for previous instructions, nothing of that is going to work.
So have a go is fun.
I want to build some more credibility.
More than 10,000 players is used by enterprises
around the world, and they have a hill tone over time.
And it's all about.
You are on the application layer here, starting from the model up at the top.
You don't have to do anything else because we are using
real models behind the scenes from OpenAI for free.
You can't do that using your GitHub account.
Today we started with this problem that there is one application security
specialist for every 100 developers, and we went through different use
cases in order for you to close this gap so you can write safer code,
you can use MCP and skills in the way that they are intended for.
Of course, you should apply
best security practices everywhere you can find and fix security box.
It suggests us to to do that in the PR, you can make better supply
chain decisions. You can have security guidelines.
And of course never forget about tailored answers you can get with AI.
You can try everything we saw for free and educate yourself about the latest
with this repo here that you can play directly from your browser in two minutes.
And with that one minute ago.
So we are doing good today.
You can't connect with me in this QR code that you are free to trust.
It's not going to drive by download anything.
I'm around the conference today more than happy
to chat about AI in general, not just the world.
I'll try my best to help you.
And with that, I want to thank you.
You've been a fantastic audience.
I was seeing the notes around and it was helpful.
Thank you so much.
Amazing.
I have never seen timing like that.
That was unbelievable.
I we.
Because I told you as a seasoned professional.
So we have five minutes for questions.
Does anyone have a question.
Excellent.
I could use more time of the presentation.
You have five minutes. Okay.
Thanks for the talk.
I had a question about one of the things you mentioned fairly
early was the risk of kind of hallucinations and false positives.
And the thing about most organizations treat security vulnerabilities
very, very seriously.
And there is a probably quite a comprehensive process
when an issue is raised.
So an AI security review that brings up five false positives can can take
a tremendous amount of time
from a development team because of the seriousness of that.
I think you mentioned something about making sure that the people that are doing
these reviews
kind of have the right domain knowledge
and things like that, but do you have any kind of it's
almost more of an organizational problem than, than a technical problem.
But like, how do you avoid that that time burn from AI disclosure abilities?
Let's take a step back.
How you can improve your AI approach,
so that what is given in front of you as a human is as curated as possible,
because that's going to help at the end result as well.
So different approaches,
different budgets, different taste and so on.
One approach can
be that you are using different models.
This is because they have different trainings.
They might find different stuff.
So two different models, if you aggregate them
you might get more problems to play with.
You might have an approach
that you are running these models more times.
Therefore you only get the results that are common between the runs
and then you aggregate them.
Every time you run, the cost goes up.
You can have the approach that and
this is an area that static tooling definitely has to improve.
And we are taking active steps on that.
You shouldn't care too much to build that DIY.
It should be you trust a company GitHub sim
grep sneak you, you name it, and the moment
you push code, you don't care what happens behind the scenes.
It's their job to combine static testing
with AI testing and maybe another round of AI
reasoning all above them to give you the best results they are at the end.
We are actively working on that.
It's an area that we have to improve, because I think the most waste of time
for developers is when they lose confidence that the results
of static, traditional testing with pattern matching
is not going to add value to a world where we moved in the execution layer
and the vulnerabilities are on the behavior of these agents.
So when it comes to the developers, they'll have to spend time on on this.
I think it touches back on education.
Traditionally,
technology has been done in a way that developers are learning
how to add functionality, but they didn't learn how to do that.
I don't want to be like speaking hundred percent,
but most developers didn't think that the job of somebody else.
Companies have a hard time to educate developers
about security video based trainings after bullying.
They don't work.
There are some other trainings out there that they are like
who wants to be millionaire kind of approach.
They give you four options and you choose one.
In my experience, security.
You can introduce more vulnerabilities by that.
There are no guarantees you are going to fix that.
There are more than 100 ways.
That's exactly why I created that training that I was telling you here.
The guy
is hands on.
That's the number one thing you get from there.
So I believe that Chief Security, if I was a chief security officer,
I will push down to my developer teams service level objectives
about expectations I have that are tied tightly
aligned with their performance objective.
So it's not about shipping code.
It's about shipping code that is secure.
Because if the code is not secure, it's not quality code.
Therefore I will tell them, you know, at the end of each sprint,
this is your allowance for open
security problems with that specific severity score.
And anything else is not accepted because you don't pass
the service level objectives.
This is me giving you context experience by working with enterprises
and trying all the other things with champions and non scalable things.
I'm sure people in the room
have experience with other approaches that worked.
In my view.
I will follow that one so that developers are educated
and when the problems arrive to them, they have the objectives
and the knowledge to the incentives and the lineage to fix those.
Thank you.
I wanted to make sure I answer.
You have a question?
Yeah.
Please. Quick.
Very quick question, please.
Do you use AI as judge in these kind of setup that you have, for example,
in any one of the patterns that's kind of gaining attention right
now is instead of focusing on just one AI model to do all the checking.
So you are referring to a judge. Perfect.
Yeah, I use that approach.
Microsoft is using that approach as well in Azure
to make sure for the understand policies, I will not explain it.
So give me 1.5 minute here.
So this technique is working.
It's not perfect for those
that might not be familiar, known as dual or as a jury.
The whole idea is that you have a second LLM judging the work of the first LLM.
So the second LLM you can ask questions like is this first LM
going to leak some sensitive information.
Actually
you can try this technique is part of that thing.
Season three level three level for its implemented in there.
I put all the latest stuff in there.
Azure is using that technique to answer questions in production.
Something like is the user trying to hack me?
Is it trying to do this? Do that?
This technique is nice.
It's working. It's not perfect.
People are bypassing it by saying, I'm not care.
I'm trying to test.
I'm not an admin and the VM has to give a deterministic answer, right?
So is this a hacking attempt yes or no?
The more I try, the more I hack it, because
when I run it ten times, I'm successful the three times.
And an attacker has to succeed once.
No matter how much you defend and how much budget
you spend in everything in your company.
So it's working.
It's a good mitigation, but it's a mitigation
if you don't plan output filtering, input filtering.
I'm not a big fan because you restrict AI input.
So if you don't do output filtering, if you don't do the number one thing,
least privilege access, right?
AI shouldn't be touching anything sensitive because as Hume, it's
going to take it.
Use it liquid agents should they be negotiating any boundaries.
So that's the number one thing.
Don't give access to anything that AI shouldn't have access.
Use containers and then
use LLMs, jewelry output validation and so on as a mitigations.
Right? Perfect.
Thanks so much. Great questions.
Thank you so much.
That's our first talk.
I have something cool to say, which is that every talk you see at
this conference is going to be turned into a skill
that you can install on your agent, and you can then be like, hey,
how do I get the most out of Joseph's talk in my code base today?
And it should it should work.
I'll. Tell you. Cool.
But if you have questions for Joseph, please find him.
There's now a coffee break.
Talks will resume in this room at 1105.
Thank you everyone. Thank you. Lacey.